[Music]
start with a semi-circle of radius one
then take the radius and rotate it a
fixed angle
the radius has length one and let's call
the angle created t drop a perpendicular
chord from the endpoint of the radius on
the circle down to the horizontal
diameter the length of this chord is the
sine of t
the third leg of the triangle formed by
the radius and this chord has length
cosine of t so that the remainder of the
horizontal radius has length one minus
the cosine of t
[Music]
the line connecting the other end of the
horizontal diameter to the endpoint of
the radius creates this triangle which
is isosceles because it has two
congruent sides
the supplementary angle to t is 180
minus t and because the other two angles
must be equal they must be
both t over two
but then
t over two is an angle inside
of this highlighted right triangle
so that the tangent of t over 2
is equal
to the sine of t
over 1 plus the cosine of t
furthermore if we create this line
segment we have built a large right
angle triangle by thaley's triangle
theorem and consequently the two
highlighted subtriangles must be similar
equating the leg ratios then tells us
that the sine of t over one plus the
cosine of t
is equal to one minus the cosine of t
over the sine of t
the semicircle has given us two formulas
for the tangent of half an angle
[Music]
you